Okay בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*, today's דף *daf* is י *yud*, we
pick up with the new פרק *perek* at the bottom of ט
עמוד ב *Tes amud-bet*. We just finished the description of how they
would actually take the money out of the room, which was called
תרומת הלשכה trumat halishka, *trumas halishka*, they're removing the תרומה truma, *truma*
of the fund from the לשכה lishkah *lishka*. We actually saw quite
interestingly how this was made similar to an act of taking תרומה
Trumah *truma* and what was remainder was called שיריים Shiyarayim, *shirayim* and
the whole question what you would do with it and would it
remain sanctified or so on. We'll be revisiting that very briefly. This
פרק *perek* focuses us on the question of what they actually would
do with the fund. So let's take a look. We've been saying
along that they would go for קרבנות ציבור korbanos tzibur *korbanos tzibur*,
let's see what's included in that category. Okay, so bottom of ט
עמוד ב *Tes amud-bet*. התרומה מה היו עושין בה *Hatruma mah hayu
osin bah*, what would they do with the תרומה Trumah *truma*? Again,
note it's the phrase of the word תרומה Trumah. *truma*, it's not
saying like what would they do with the שקלים *shekalim*. So again,
this is very much focusing on this as תרומה Trumah *truma*. לוקחין
בה תמידין ומוספין ונסכיהם *Lokchin ba temidin umusafin veniskeyhen*. So basically you
would buy קרבנות ציבור korbanot tzibur *korbanos tzibur*, so the תמידין *temidin*,
the two daily sacrifices, the מוסף *musaf*, which would mostly be an
עולה ola, *ola* plus a חטאת chatat. *chatas*, but a lot of
animals that were an עולה *ola*, and the נסכים nesachim *nisachim*, the
wine and the grain and the flour offering that would come along
with them, all of the קרבנות ציבור korbanot tzibur *korbanos tzibur* with
their attendant things that were offered on the מזבח mizbe'ach *mizbeach*. העומר
ושתי הלחם v'shtei halechem. ולחם הפנים *Ha'omer ushtey halechem v'lechem hapanim*. Now
other things that are not animal related also but that are קרבנות
ציבור korbanot tzibbur. *korbanos tzibur*, there are מנחות *minchos* that are קרבן
ציבור Korban Tzibur, *korban tzibur*. העומר *Ha'omer* and שתי הלחם shtei halechem
*shtey halechem* for פסח Pesach, *Pesach* and שבועות *Shavuos*, and לחם הפנים
*lechem hapanim*, that also would be a type of a קרבן ציבור
korban tzibbur *korban tzibur* that would come from the communal fund. וכל
קרבנות korbanos, הציבור *V'chol korbanos hatzibur*, and any קרבן ציבור korban tzibbur
*korban tzibur*. Of course, if this was the בבלי Bavli *Bavli*, you
would expect it to say כל לרבות מאי *kol l'rabos mai*, you
know, what's that coming to include that we didn't already say? ירושלמי
Yerushalmi *Yerushalmi* doesn't even ask the question. What? It is a משנה
Mishnah, *mishna*, I understand, but I'm telling you when we get to
the גמרא Gemara, *gemara* it's not going to ask the question. שומרי
ספיחין sefichin, בשביעית *Shomrey sfiachin beshviis*. Now we had mentioned עומר Omer?
*omer*, so now we're going to talk about an interesting aspect of
the עומר Omer. *omer*. The people that watch the wild growth on
שמיטה Shemita *Shemita*, on שביעית Shevi'it. *shviis*, נותנים שכר מתרומת הלשכה *notnim
schar mitrumas halishka*. They get paid from the תרומת הלשכה trumat halishka,
*trumas halishka*. What does it mean? It means during the שמיטה Shmita
*Shemita* year you do not plant the grain that's going to be
brought for the עומר Omer. *omer*. So how what what grain are
you taking it from? So you're taking it from the grain that
is growing like just spontaneously from dropped seeds and you know, the
wild growth. Okay, but you have to make sure that you that
you have what to cut. So you have to hire people to
watch certain stuff to make sure that other people don't get it,
and just saying why that's not a violation of שמיטה Shmita *Shemita*
because you're not supposed to protect the stuff like you're the owner,
but okay, but they're doing it also for the בית דין Beit
Din *Beis Din* and for the מקדש Mikdash *Mikdash* and for כלל
ישראל Klal Yisrael, *Klal Yisrael* and so on. And then when it's
ready they harvest it and they take possession of it for the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, *Beis HaMikdash*. But the point is you gotta
hire people to do this. Okay, so you can actually pay their
fee from the money of the תרומת הלשכה Trumat Halishkah, *trumas halishka*
although you're not paying for the actual object itself.
Nevertheless, that is acceptable. Basically the principle here is צורכי קרבן tzorchei
korban, כקרבן *tzorchey korban k'korban*. So you can pay the things that
are needed for the to make it possible to bring the קרבן
korban *korban* from those funds as well. That opens up a huge
range of possibilities which some of which we will discuss, we will
discuss.
So you can pay actually their fee. רבי יוסי אומר Rabbi Yosei
omer, אף הרוצה מתנדב שומר חינם *Rabbi Yosi omer af harotzeh mitnadeiv
shomer chinam*. Rabbi Yosi says, you know, you don't even have to
use money to do that, because somebody who basically cut their own
wheat on שמיטה Shmita *Shemita* and is protecting, you know, watching sort
of, watching it for free, hey, I'll watch it for the sake
of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beis HaMikdash*, and then goes ahead
and he's not hired by the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. *Beis HaMikdash*,
and he harvests it and then he gives it as a gift
to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. *Beis HaMikdash*. So you can do
this for free. Maybe he was more tentative about using the funds
to pay for secondary needs of the קרבן korban *korban*. So rather
than using the funds to pay for the שומרים *shomrim*, he says
let somebody just do it and donate, you know, donate their time
and go ahead and do it for free. אמרו לו *Amru lo*,
so they said to him, אף אתה אומר שאין באין אלא משל
ציבור Tzibur. *af ata omer she'ein ba'in ela mishel tzibur*, no, but
don't you have to admit that you can only bring the קרבנות
korbanos. *korbanos* from communal sacrifices, from things that were, you know, sort
of purchased communally? So this is going to be a question, thank
you, that we're going to look in the גמרא Gemara *gemara* which
is, can I as an individual make a private donation to the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. *Beis HaMikdash* for the sake of something to
be used as a as a communal sacrifice? I come with my
sheep and I say I would like this sheep, I'm giving it
over wholeheartedly to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. *Beis HaMikdash* for the
purpose of כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael. *Klal Yisrael*, I want you to
use it for a תמיד *tamid*. Can I do that or not?
And that is the debate here. So when the חכמים Chachamim? *Chachamim*
don't want somebody to watch it privately and then give it, cut
it themselves and give it, that's because it becomes a personal, their
personal wheat that then they are donating. And that's for the חכמים
Chachamim is not acceptable for a קרבן ציבור, korban tzibbur. we have
to buy it with communal funds. We don't want private donation even
for communal causes. Now, the reason could be, we'll see in the
גמרא, Gemara. you could say that somebody never sort of sincerely fully
gives it over and it never really becomes owned by the ציבור.
tzibur. We'll see in the גמרא Gemara that that's not true because
the rabbis are prepared to have it done for other things that
are communal, just not for the communal sacrifices. So you don't, let's
actually think about what that would, the debate would be about and
we'll talk about it and then we'll see the גמרא. Gemara Yes,
Charlie.
But we just had רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel sort of make a
distinguish private donation.
That was giving his private שקל shekel but in the end it
was mixed with the communal funds. He wasn't saying "here's my sheep,
be מקריב makriv this as a קרבן". korban Okay? Now again, you
could understand that the problem would be that even if technically it's
owned by כלל ישראל, Klal Yisrael, the guy's still going to say,
"Look, you see that? That's mine. You see the עומר? Omer That
was my wheat that went there." And then it would lose some
of that communal nature to
it.
Private donation, communal party. Exactly.
So let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara on this. So
interestingly, the גמרא Gemara skips over the beginning of the משנה, Mishnah.
goes to the second part, this exact debate, and will double back
to the beginning of the משנה. Mishnah So let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara. says like
this: מה ראו? Mah ra'u? Okay, מה ראו? Mah ra'u? Now this
is
basically a discussion that exists also in the, it's transported but it
will be relevant from a משנה Mishnah in תענית. Taanis. The משנה
Mishna in תענית Taanis says that there were eight times which was
זמן עצי הכהנים והעם. zman atzei hakohanim ve'ha'am. Eight times where there
were eight dates that were set aside for contributions of wood to
the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash. and this was by eight families. Each
family had their own date, and we're going to see in a
minute that was based on a certain historical event. So basically, although
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash would use communal funds, it's going to
be an interesting question here, anything that is communal, which funds does
it come from? Because we're now saying that the שקל shekel is
only used for the קרבנות, korbanos but there's a lot of things
that need to be communally owned that are not just קרבנות. korbanot,
Where are they going to come from? That's coming up משניות, mishnayos,
we're going to see where all the different things come from. But
anyway, the wood is supposed to be communal, right? It's owned by
the ציבור. And nevertheless, these eight families would have their eight dates
where they would make their donations of the wood to the communal,
you know, wood stores. So for the בית המקדש. Beis haMikdash So
isn't that part of this debate of רבי יוסי Rebbi Yose and
the חכמים? Chachamim. Can you accept a private donation of an object
that needs to be used communally? So that's what, why we're bringing
this in. So let's take a look. מה ראו עצי זמן עצי
הכהנים והעם להימנות? Mah ra'u atzei zman atzei hakohanim ve'ha'am le'himanos? Why
were these eight dates sort of counted and, you know, identified? So
אלא בשעה, Ella besha'ah, this is the ברייתא, Baraisa, so בשעה שעלו
ישראל מן הגולה, Besha'ah she'alu Yisrael min hagolah, when they returned from
the exile in the time of עזרא, Ezra, ולא מצאו עצים בלשכה,
Velo matzu etzim balishkah, and there was no, you know, wood. There
was no a lot of things, they had to rebuild the whole,
it's so funny the phrase "there was no wood in the לשכה".
lishkah There was no בית המקדש. Beis haMikdash. They rebuilt the בית
המקדש. Beis haMikdash, Anyway, one of the things they needed, there was
a time when they were over, you know, they needed, they needed
to load up their wood stores. ועמדו אלו ונתנדבו. Ve'amdu elu ve'nisnadvu.
And these eight families got up and they made donations to, you
know, store up the wood stores of the בית המקדש. Beis haMikdash.
ונתנדבו עצים משל עצמם, Ve'nisnadvu etzim mishel atzmam, and they gave over,
you know, their own wood. ומסרום לציבור, U'mesarum latzibur, and they freely
gave it over to the, you know, for the sake of כלל
ישראל. Klal Yisrael והקריבו מהם קרבנות ציבור, Ve'hikrivu mehem korbanos tzibur, and
they used that wood to bring קרבנות ציבור korbanot tzibbur, on them,
on the wood, the fires that they made on the מזבח mizbe'ach.
with the wood. והתנו עמהם נביאים שביניהם, Ve'hisnu imahem nevi'im shebeineihem, and
the prophets among them, presumably חגי זכריה ומלאכי Chaggai, Zechariah, u'Malachi who
were the last of the prophets, you know, sort of stipulated or,
you know, made a pact.
והתנו עמהם נביאים שביניהם, Ve'hisnu imahem nevi'im shebeineihem, שאפילו לשכה מלאה עצים,
She'afillu lishkah meleiah etzim, even in the future, even at times when
the storehouses will be filled with wood, ועמדו אלו ונתנדבו עצים משל
עצמם, Ve'amdu elu ve'nisnadvu etzim mishel atzmam, if you families want to
be giving your own wood donations, it's a funny phrase because it's
not only "want to," it actually seems like, you know, these eight
dates were dates where they had a
standing practice to give. Anyway, שלא יהא קרבן מתקרב אלא משלהם תחילה.
Shelo yehei korban miskarev ella mishelahem techilah. We would a) take your
wood donations, we wouldn't say no we already have enough wood, and
b) we would use your donations to be the first thing we
would bring the קרבנות korbanot. on. So you give these eight, these
eight various dates, each family has a date, that's a date you
bring your big, you know, stuff of wood to the בית המקדש.
Beis haMikdash? And in, you know, sort of in commemoration of how
your family was so instrumental at the early stage, we'll take that
wood and that will be the wood that we'll start using this
week, you know, on the מזבח. mizbeach, So look, isn't this exactly
this debate of רבי יוסי Rebbi Yose and the חכמים Chachamim where
you accept private donations? If anything, it's even more problematic here because
the whole thing they have a whole big date and a holiday
and it's labeled as that family's and you make sure to use
it first. So isn't this part of this debate? That's what the
גמרא Gemara says. Exactly. Well not their say their wood and that's
going to be important for the גמרא. Gemara So let's see the
גמרא's Gemara answer. So אמר רבי יכא דרבי יוסי. Amar Rabbi Yacha
d'Rabbi Yose. So he says that whole idea that they allowed this
to happen all follows the approach of רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. דרבי
יוסי אומר אף הרוצה מתנדב שומר חנם. d'Rabbi Yose omer af harotze
mitnadave shomer chinam. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says you can contribute your
free time to watch the grain and presumably then you'd take possession
of the grain and give the grain that grew on שמיטה Shmita
for the עומר. Omer So you see you can accept private donations.
רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, now just to make things confusing, now we
have רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose the אמורא, Amora, some have רב אסי.
Rav Assi. But anyway רבי יוסי משמיה דרבי אילא, Rabbi Yose mishme
d'Rabbi Ila, no, דיברי הכל היא. divrei hakol hi. That משנה Mishna
could be going like everybody. מה פליגן? Mah peligan? When do the
rabbis and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose in our משנה Mishna? debate? בגוף
דקרבן Beguf d'korban relating to the actual thing that is going to
be offered itself, the קרבן korban, itself, can you take that from
a private donation? אבל במכשירי קרבן, Aval bemachshirei korban, things that enable
the קרבן korban. to be brought like the wood, כל עמא מודו,
kol ama modei, everybody agrees, שהיא משתנה קרבן יחיד לקרבן ציבור. shehi
mishtaneh korban yachid lekorban tzibbur. You can take something that was private
and make it for and use it for a communal, not literally
קרבן, korban. but for communal purposes. So we can take private donations
and use the thing itself not just the fund but we won't
do it for a קרבן. korban Again the question becomes is this
a concern of more about like appearances that we're particularly sensitive by
קרבן ציבור korban tzibbur, that nobody says that's my קרבן. korban You
want to say those are my that's my wood being used, go
ahead. But to say that's my קרבן korban when the whole idea
is that this is being brought for כלל ישראל, Israel this is
the עיקר, ikar, עיקר ikar is what's put on the מזבח, mizbe'ach.
everything else is like a sideshow, but that thing that is for
the community- that is for כלל ישראל nobody should make a personal
claim about it. So is it about you know so it seems
like it's something about more more like a policy issue if you
would that we don't want people sort of identifying it. You could
have is it also actually a strict halakhic objective point? Does somehow
the fact that it started as an individual's and he gave it
over you know as a private donation I mean everything starts as
individuals but if you use communal funds to buy it then that
then it was purchased communally. Here it started the individual and it
was the individual's gift that made it possible does that somehow undermine
its status as a קרבן korban ציבור even objectively forget policy considerations?
So that's not so clear exactly what the difference is between why
we'll accept it for the attendant issues but not for the קרבן
korban itself. And now we're going to have another
similar ברייתא beraita with a similar debate. So let's take a look.
אית
תני, Ish tani, we taught in a ברייתא. beraita. אשה שעשתה כותנת
לבנה. Isha sheasta kutonet livnah. So if a woman made, it's interesting
we're going to see this in a little bit later too, when
it talks about weaving and sewing it always brings in women. If
a woman made a white tunic, כשרה, keshera, it can be used
for the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol on יום כיפור Yom Kippur ובלבד
שתמסרנה לציבור uvilvad shetimserena letzibbur as long as she freely gives it
over to the entire community. So אמר רבי יכא דרבי יוסי Amar
Rabbi Yacha d'Rabbi Yose that follows רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. רבי יוסי
אומר אף הרוצה מתנדב שומר חנם Rabbi Yose omer af harotze mitnadave
shomer chinam you can donate your time and basically donate the wheat
so you can donate the white tunic that the כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol will use on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. רבי יוסי בשם אילא,
Rabbi Yose beshem Ila, no, דיברי הכל היא, divrei hakol hi, everybody
agrees to this. מה פליגן? Mah peligan? What's the debate in the
משנה? Mishna בגוף דקרבן Beguf d'korban by the קרבן korban, itself. אבל
במכשירי קרבן Aval bemachshirei korban anything else that enables the קרבן korban
to be brought, כל עמא מודו, kol ama modei, שהיא משתנה קרבן
יחיד לקרבן ציבור. shehi mishtaneh korban yachid lekorban tzibbur. Everybody says you
can take a private donation and make it use for communal purposes.
It's quite interesting because you would think that the clothes of the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol on יום כיפור Yom Kippur you know would
more a little bit more be in the קרבן עצמו korban atzmo
category. I mean obviously formalistically it isn't anything other than the קרבן
korban. is just the things that enable the עבודה avoda to be
done. One of the things that enable the עבודה avoda is that
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is wearing the right בגדים. bigadim. But
again it is interesting thinking about why we are drawing the line
exactly at the קרבן, korban the ירושלמי Yerushalmi never tells us why
that is the one category that we are focusing on yes.
Well particularly the יום כיפור Yom Kippur בגדים bigadim because they're only
used once. Right.
So you might more oh so you mean so therefore what you
might more want to take private donations or you're more or you're
more concerned about private donations?
Not well no you're I think you'd be less concerned because that
really is only going to be used by that one כהן kohen
ever.
So for that one day maybe it's not such an issue maybe.
But anyway it's not what the גמרא Gemara? says. The גמרא Gemara
says it's all about the קרבן korban for the חכמים. Chachamim Okay
now we're going to מתניתין פליגי אל רבי יוסי. matnisin peligei al
Rabbi Yose. The משנה Mishna. argues on רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. אותם
ימים נוהגים בשעת קרבן ושלא בשעת קרבן Otam yamim nohagim beshaat korban
ushelo beshaat korban because we teach that those days I'm sorry it's
a ברייתא beraita not a משנה. mishna. Those days the days those
eight days of donations of the wood are practiced as sort of
you know family יום טובים yom tovs for the families that donated
it whether it was the time of קרבנות, korbanot the time of
the בית המקדש Beis haMikdash. ושלא בשעת קרבן ushelo beshaat korban or
not the time of קרבנות. korbanot, It's interesting you know in the
בבלי Bavli it would always be בזמן. bizman. בית המקדש post-Beis haMikdash.
or, you know, אפילו שלא בזמן בית המקדש. afilu shelo bizman Beis
haMikdash. He uses the phrases בשעת קרבן b'shat korban ושלא בשעת קרבן.
v'shelo b'shat korban. Interesting different use. Of course, the point is the
wood was used for the קרבן. korban. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei אומר,
אינם נוהגים אלא בשעת קרבן בלבד. eynam nohagim ella b'shat korban bilvad.
They only have those holidays at the time when there were קרבנות
korbanot, at the time of the בית המקדש. Beis haMikdash, Now what
does this do to prove a challenge to רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei
or to prove a challenge? Now when it says פליגא דרבי יוסי,
pliga d'Rabbi Yosei, it does not mean רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei of
the משנה. Mishna It means the רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei, אמורא amora
we quoted before, which is just to make things confusing on you.
So the point is the following: that if you see the חכמים
Chachamim argue on רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosei and they say that these
days apply, so look, you see that the חכמים Chachamim who argue
on רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei, agree that these eight days were eight
holidays and that they accept the whole institution of these eight days.
So the argument before was that only רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosei according
to one אמורא, amora, would allow for this institution of the days
of contributing the wood. The חכמים Chachamim would not allow for the
contributing of the wood because it was a private thing becoming public.
So you see it's not true. You see the חכמים Chachamim and
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei? debate whether it applies not in the time
of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash but they all agree that the
institution of the donating of the wood was done by these families.
So they all agree, you see, that it doesn't even the חכמים
Chachamim. agree we would allow the donations of the wood. Now the
problem is that who is the one who said that even the
חכמים Chachamim would allow these donations? It was רבי יוסי בשם רבי
אילא. Rabbi Yosei beshem Rabbi Ila. So what does it mean it
argues on רבי יוסי? Rabbi Yosei, So everybody switches the גירסא. girsa.
Either they make the גירסא girsa say this agrees with רבי יוסי,
Rabbi Yosei, this supports רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosei or they say it
argues on רבי אחא Rabbi Acho because רבי אחא Rabbi Acho was
the one that said it would be a debate between רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosei and the חכמים. Chachamim You're looking for your גמרא? Gemara
I don't know where it is. Okay. We are missing several
גמרות? Gemaras? All right. I don't know what to say. All
right, anyway, there's some גמרות Gemaras over on top of the חומשים
Chumashim over there. Oh, all right, anyway. All right, so that is,
so this proves that even the חכמים Chachamim would agree to the
institution of the donating of the wood and that supports either it
supports רבי יוסי'ס Rabbi Yosei's רבי אסי'ס בשם רבי אילא'ס Rabbi Assi's
beshem Rabbi Ila's argument that the חכמים Chachamim would agree and it
contradicts רבי אחא'ס Rabbi Acho's argument. So now the גמרא Gemara says
ועוד מן הדא, v'od min hada, and another proof that the חכמים
Chachamim agree that you can accept private donations as long as it's
not the קרבן korban itself, from the following דתניא d'tanya we taught
in the
ברייתא: braita: אמר רבי אליעזר בי רבי צדוק אנו היינו מבני סנאה
בן בנימין. Amar Rabbi Eliezer bei Rabbi Tzadok anu hayinu mi'bnei San'ah
ben Binyamin. So the house of רבי צדוק Rabbi Tzadok said that
we are descendants of the house of סנאה בן בנימין. San'ah ben
Binyamin. סנאה בן בנימין San'ah ben Binyamin was one of the eight
families, okay. וחל תשעה באב להיות בשבת. v'chal Tisha B'Av lihyot b'Shabbat.
Now that family, you know which day that family had as their
holiday? The tenth of אב. Av. Okay, so that's getting pretty close
to תשעה באב. Tisha B'Av. And here's an interesting story that happened
once: וחל תשעה באב להיות בשבת. v'chal Tisha B'Av lihyot b'Shabbat. One
year תשעה באב Tisha B'Av fell out on שבת. Shabbat. So when
do you have תשעה באב, Tisha B'Av, when do you do it?
On the tenth of אב. Av. That tenth of אב Av was
the holiday for this family. So what did we do? ודחינו אותו
למוצאי שבת. v'dachinu oto l'motza'ei Shabbat. תשעה באב Tisha B'Av was pushed
off to מוצאי שבת, motza'ei Shabbat, and that was the same day
as our family's holiday because of these wood donations. והיינו מתענים ולא
משלימים. v'hayinu mit'anim v'lo m'shlimin. Because it was our holiday, we began
the fast but we didn't finish the fast, we didn't even do
the whole fast of תשעה באב. Tisha B'Av. That's how powerful this
holiday was, this family holiday was, that it was given this recognition
that it could even override the fast of תשעה באב, Tisha B'Av,
you wouldn't have to complete it. Now why is that relevant? It's
relevant because it shows that again, the idea
of these holidays was practiced after the time of the בית המקדש.
Beit Hamikdash. How do you know that was after the time of
the בית המקדש? Beit Hamikdash, Because you're having a תשעה באב. Tisha
B'Av. Okay, you wouldn't have a תשעה באב Tisha B'Av during the
time of the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. They did have a תשעה
באב Tisha B'Av in between the times, the first reference to it
is in ירמיהו, Yirmiyahu, but anyway, but you're having a תשעה באב
Tisha B'Av it shows it's post-בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash And we know
that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei doesn't hold of the idea of this
as a יום טוב. yom tov. So obviously again, the חכמים Chachamim
hold that this יום טוב yom tov applies even after the בית
המקדש, Beit Hamikdash which means the חכמים chachamim accept the idea that
you could take these private donations of wood. So the חכמים Chachamim
don't disagree with רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi, that you can take private
donations on things not related to קרבנות, korbanot they only disagree about
the actual קרבן korban, itself. Yes, דב? Dov? No, you have your
hand up? Do you have your hand up? Okay, yes, about what
you were doing with תשעה באב. Tisha B'Av. Right, now you know,
yes.
What about this concept of a personal יום טוב? yom tov? That's
a very interesting idea.
So you know what? We can...
yes,
have communal פורים קטן,
Purim Katan, personal fast days, and there's also personal יום טובs yom
tov on a day that there was a נס. nes. So when
we learn תענית, Taanis, we'll get to it. We only have to...
actually, תענית Taanis is coming up within the year, okay, so don't
worry, hold that thought. Okay, so now we continue. האומר, Ha'omer, now
we're in... double back. So that was fascinating, whether you take private
donations of the objects themselves and the גמרא Gemara's is saying that
everybody would say it's okay except and the whole debate is just
for the קרבן. korban And now we double back to the discussion
about the עומר. Omer, האומר ושתי הלחם ולחם הפנים וכל קרבנות ציבור
Ha'omer v'Shtei HaLechem v'Lechem HaPanim v'chol korbanos tzibur all those things you
would use the שקל, shekel, the communal funds to buy. So the
גמרא Gemara says so
you know we can let's first read the parentheses it'll come up
again but we might as well read it here it's also relevant
here. מתניתין דרבי ישמעאל, Masnisin d'Rabbi Yishmael, our משנה Mishna is רבי
ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. דרבי ישמעאל אומר אין עומר בא מן הסוריא. D'Rabbi
Yishmael omer ein omer ba min haSurya. So the עומר Omer can
only come from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, it can't come from סוריא.
Surya. סוריא Surya was a nearby lands, lands that were conquered by
דוד המלך, Dovid HaMelech, you know, Jordan and so on, and they
had there was a whole question about their קדושה kedusha for as
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael or not. Now what does where do you
see in the משנה Mishna whether the עומר Omer can come from
סוריא Surya or not? So the following reason: why do you have
to hire people to watch wild growth on שמיטה Shmita? in order
to harvest it to bring the עומר, Omer why not just bring
it from stuff that was grown in סוריא? Surya? Okay, so you
must you see that our משנה Mishna, obviously holds that the only
place you can bring the עומר Omer from is from ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael and therefore you're going to have special challenges during the
שמיטה Shmita year. Now of course you could say maybe in סוריא
Surya if the same if you can bring the עומר Omer from
it maybe שמיטה Shmita, applies by it. But somehow the גמרא's Gemara
understanding is that it's possible that you could bring the עומר Omer
from סוריא Surya and the laws of שמיטה Shmita? would not apply
or at least not biblically apply and it would have been a
lot easier. So if we have to pay for people to watch
the grain from wild growth that means that our only option is
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Yes. What?
When would you harvest it from סוריא? Surya? By the way, today's
journey is several days' journey. Yeah, oh so you're so okay.
You have to harvest
it that day.
That's a good point, but I think בדיעבד bedi'eved you don't have
to. I mean they would harvest it in the morning but it's
ראשית קצירכם reishis ktzirchem but it is true that the קצירת העומר
ktziras ha'omer is דוחה את שבת. doche es Shabbos. So right so
that is an issue but I think
בדיעבד bedi'eved a good question I think בדיעבד bedi'eved even if it's
even not on the day itself. I mean we do say קצירת
העומר ktziras ha'omer is דוחה שבת doche Shabbos which would indicate it
has to be the day itself. Let me I'll check into that.
Mordechai, you had a question?
Yeah, I mean you could ask this question about any of the
מנחה mincha offerings. You usually had to just stockpile enough grain for
a whole year's worth of מנחה mincha offerings.
Yeah, so what what's your question?
So I mean you can't run out where do you get the
grain for the?
Oh you mean during the ספירה Sefira period? I mean during the
during the עומר Omer period. Yeah,
yeah, I mean you could do your private Look, people the grain
wasn't אסור assur people could grab you know take their own grain
for the private ones. The only issue was the communal sacrifices and
the only communal מנחה mincha well, it's actually not true because you
did have the כהן גדול's Kohen Gadol's מנחה mincha מנחה mincha that
was brought every day. But that was I think his private one.
So he could have so he could right so but I think
it's true for any communal one you'd have to handle in a
similar fashion. All right, so let's keep on going. But it is
a good question about whether cutting the עומר Omer, not on the
same day. Okay, so it says like this: תנינא, Tanina, we taught
in the משנה, Mishna famous משנה Mishna in כלים: Kelim: עשר קדושות
הן, eser kedushos hein, there are ten things that are holy in
terms of geography, each level getting holier than the next. ארץ ישראל
מקודשת מכל הארצות, Eretz Yisrael mekudeshes mikol ha'aratzos, the land of Israel
more than all other lands, ומה היא קדושתה u'mah hi kedushashah what's
its holiness? שמביאים ממנה העומר והביכורים ושתי הלחם shemevi'im mimenah ha'omer v'habikurim
u'shtei halechem only from things that grow in the land of Israel
can you bring the עומר Omer, and ביכורים bikurim and the שתי
הלחם shtei halechem and they learn this from פסוקים psukim like here
some of the פסוקים psukim are quoted here let me let me
get it to you,
let's see hold on,
by
שתי הלחם it says ממושבותיכם mimoshvoseichem by the עומר Omer it says
וקצרתם את קצירה, v'ktzartem es ktzirah, so קצירה ktzirah means the cutting
of the land, okay, and so anyway so from all of these
there's a פסוק pasuk to say that they only come from ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Now by the way you could say there's a
lot of other things that make ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael holy. What
about the fact that it was the land that was promised to
אברהם Avraham and so on? But this is talking about very much
as it were almost the holiness of the dirt, you know, of
the of the land, you know, not of the country. So so
the way in which that is demonstrated is only from the grain
that grows in that land can you bring the עומר, Omer ביכורים,
bikurim, ושתי הלחם. רבי חייה בשם רבי ירמיה, Rabbi Chiya b'shem Rabbi
Yirmiya, דורבי ישמעאל היא. d'Rabbi Yishmael hi. Now רבי חייה Rabbi Chiya
in the name of רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiya says that actually משנה
Mishna is going according to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, דרבי ישמעאל אומר
אין עומר בא מסוריא d'Rabbi Yishmael omer ein omer ba miSurya
because he says it can only be from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael,
but apparently there are other opinions that say that it could actually
be from סוריא Surya and it's not limited to ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisrael. Again, it's funny which רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael are they quoting?
Did he just have a tradition that רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael disagreed?
Is it a ברייתא braisa that he's quoting? I mean we're always
referencing a רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael but we haven't exactly quoted a
tannaic source directly that said it. Okay, but again this idea that
according to Rabbi Ishmael it has to come only from ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael proper. תמן תנינן. taman taninan. Now, we taught over there
in where is this, in שביעית. Shvi'it רבי ישמעאל אומר, Rabbi Ishmael
omer, מה חריש רשות אף קציר רשות. ma charish reshut af katzir
reshut. It's going on the פסוק pasuk that says, בחריש ובקציר תשבות.
be-charish u-va-katzir tishbot. You should rest from the plowing and from the
and from the harvesting. So what's it talking about? It's very unclear
in the פסוק. pasuk. Is it talking about שבת Shabbat or is
it talking about שמיטה? Shmita Okay, so let's see what he does
with it. He says that first of all, we're talking about the
same way plowing, there's never a מצוה mitzvah to plow. Okay, so
when we say you have to cease harvesting, קציר, katzir, it means
harvesting that's a רשות. reshut. But קציר katzir that's a מצוה mitzvah
like the עומר, Omer right, there's a מצוה mitzvah וקצרתם את קצירה,
u-ktzartem et katzira, that you would not have to stop doing. Now
when would you not have to stop doing it? So there are
two times you're not allowed to harvest. What are the two times
you're not allowed to harvest? שמיטה Shmita.
and and
well yes, but and שבת. Shabbat. So he says so you'd be
allowed to harvest the עומר Omer on שמיטה, Shmita everybody would agree
with that or else how would you bring the עומר Omer, on
שמיטה? Shmita, And you're even allowed to cut the עומר Omer on
שבת. Shabbat. Okay, that the בחריש ובקציר תשבות be-charish u-va-katzir tishbot means
you only have to not harvest when it's not a מצוה. mitzvah.
When it's a מצוה mitzvah you don't have to rest either from
שמיטה Shmita or from שבת. Shabbat. One minute. So יצא קציר העומר
שהוא מצוה yatza katzir ha-Omer she-hu mitzvah to exclude the cutting of
the עומר Omer that that is a מצוה. mitzvah. And then the
גמרא Gemara says, רבי ישמעאל כדעתיה, Rabbi Ishmael ke-da'ateih, Rabbi Ishmael is
going according to his reasoning, דאמר רבי ישמעאל אין עומר בא מן
הסוריא. de-amar Rabbi Ishmael ein Omer ba min ha-Surya. It doesn't go,
it cannot come from סוריא. Surya.
כדעתיה, ke-da'ateih, that's going like his reasoning דאמר יצא קציר עומר שהוא
מצוה de-amar yatza katzir Omer she-hu mitzvah that the cutting is a
מצוה. mitzvah. Now why is that true? Why can't I cut it
from סוריא Surya and still say that it's a מצוה? mitzvah? So
the way the ירושלמי Yerushalmi is framed it makes it sound like
if I demand that it be from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, that
more almost creates a ritual and a מצוה mitzvah nature to the
cutting. But if I can cut it from סוריא, Surya, then it
doesn't really matter so much the act of cutting because I can
even bring it from out of ישראל and maybe I can't call
it a מצוה. mitzvah. That's if you take the ירושלמי at face
value. That is not how the מפרשים mefarshim say it, because that
obviously is not a rigorous argument. And what the מפרשים mefarshim say
he's saying is that if one of the things we're allowing is
cutting it on the עומר, Omer well we wouldn't need to allow
cutting it on the עומר Omer if you could bring it from
חוץ לארץ. chutz la-aretz. So part of his argument is, ah, you're
מתיר matir it to be
done even over שמיטה. Shmita. Well why would that be necessary? Now
of course it might not be necessary but still allowed. But anyway
that is that is the argument that he is going כדעתיה. ke-da'ateih.
Okay. Was there a question? No. Okay good. See now we say
like this.
That's a Babylonian argument there.
You think?
That he said that דעיקר הדין de-ikar ha-din it was אסור, assur,
but you need a מתיר. matir.
All right and as opposed to saying, you know what, it was
never אסור assur in the nature of this מצוה.
mitzvah. Right, but still the question is why you need, you mean
so then we there wouldn't be a push to do it in
סוריא. Surya. Right, that's exactly the type of a
נדחה. nidcha. Okay.
Now the גמרא Gemara says like this. So תנא שומר ספיחין בשביעית
נוטלין שכר מתרומת הלשכה. tanna shomer sefichin bi-shvi'it notlin sachar mi-trumat ha-lishka.
Now this is where we started, if we question whether we had
this גרסא girsa before, but to say that our משנה Mishna is
also like רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael because why do you have to
hire people to watch it, why can't you just bring it from
חוץ לארץ? chutz la-aretz? So רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Ishmael, that's רבי ישמעאל.
Rabbi Ishmael. So אמר רבי יוסי, amar Rabbi Yossi, no, דברי הכל
היא. divrei ha-kol hi. It's interesting the same רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi before said דברי הכל היא, divrei ha-kol hi,
right? He limited the debate of who was it, of רבי יוסי
in the משנה Mishna and the חכמים chachamim, about when you take
private donations. Here too he's limiting the debate and he says the
משנה Mishna is דברי הכל היא. divrei ha-kol hi. לא מצאו בסוריא
מביאין אותו מספיחין שבארץ ישראל. lo matzu be-Surya mevi'in oto mi-sefichin she-be-Eretz
Yisrael. There are times you have to hire people in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael to watch the grain. Let's say there's not enough grain
in סוריא. Surya. Let's say they're having a drought in סוריא. Surya.
So our משנה mishna that says you hire people in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael to watch the grain is not necessarily assuming you can
only bring it from ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. What it's assuming is
that there are times you'll have to bring it from ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael and if that's a שמיטה Shmita, and you have to
bring it from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, you'll have to hire people
with the communal funds. Okay, now we say the following. ההן אומר
מהו שייזרע בתחילה. ha-hen omer mahu she-yizarei bi-tchila. Or we spoke about
ספיחין, about wild growth. Why if maybe he should be allowed to
plant the seeds that you're going to use for the grain for
the עומר Omer on שמיטה, Shmita. right? If we allow you to
harvest on שמיטה Shmita maybe we should allow you to actually plant
the seeds, plant the seeds. Although the planting isn't a מצוה. mitzvah.
But that's the question. Maybe you should be able to plant it
on שמיטה. Shmita, רבי חייא בר אדא בעא קומי רבי מנא. Rabbi
Chiya bar Ada baei kumi Rabbi Mana. Now
here's why you can't do it. לא נמצא כקומץ על הכלאים שאינם
נאכלים. lo nimtza ke-komets al ha-kilayim she-einam ne'echalim. If you were to
do that then the grain would be אסור. assur. The assumption is
that you actually If you planted the grain on שמיטה, Shmita even
if you were allowed to do the act, what would grow would
be forbidden, it would be the product of a violation of שמיטה.
Shmita So if that's the case, he says, you can't bring the
עומר Omer. from that grain because then what's left is unable to
be eaten. Right? You take the מנחה, Mincha, you put it on
the you take the קומץ, Kometz, you put it on the altar,
the rest of the עומר Omer, is שיריים, shirayim, is what's left
over the מנחה, Mincha, it's supposed to be able to be edible.
But if you actually did not took your עומר from stuff that
was that was like violated שמיטה shemita, in order to plant it,
then it would be it would be אינם נאכלים.
einam ne'echalim. מצוה הבאה בעבירה, Mitzvah haba'ah b'aveirah,
but it's more technical in terms of the object. What the בבלי
Bavli would say at this minute is ממשקה ישראל. mimashkeh Yisrael. The
בבלי learns from a פסוק pasuk in יחזקאל Yechezkel that says ממשקה
ישראל מן המותר לישראל, mimashkeh Yisrael min hamuttar l'Yisrael, that you can't
bring a קרבן korban. from מאכלות אסורות. ma'achalot assurot. Okay, so that's
what it's saying. A מנחה, Mincha, you can't have it that it's
not able to be eaten. So אמר ליה, amar lei, so he
said back to him, no, not necessarily. נעשה כחמשה דברים שאין באין
בטומאה ואין נאכלים בטומאה. nasa k'chamishah devarim she-ein bo-in b'tumah v'ein ne'echalim
b'tumah. Don't you remember what we just learned in פסחים, Pesachim, which
is that there's five קרבנות ציבור korbanot tzibbur, that can be brought
בטומאה, b'tumah, but they can't be eaten because only the פסח, Pesach
if you remember, can be eaten בטומאה b'tumah because whole point of
the פסח was to be eaten. Other קרבנות ציבור korbanos tzibur? that
can be brought בטומאה b'tumah can't be eaten בטומאה. b'tumah. So he
says, what about that? Same story. You're מטמא metamei the קרבן, korban.
it's not fit to be eaten, and we're still able to bring
it. So if that's true by טומאה tumah that you can bring
a קרבן korban. that can't be eaten, it can be true here.
Of course, there's a bit of a difference because we have this
principle of like טומאה הותרה, tumah hutra, you know, and it might
be a special הלכה halakha of טומאה. tumah. But he's saying, you
know, so what, it's שמיטה, shemita, so let's say the same thing.
Alright, is there a שמיטה problem here? But you'll still go ahead
and bring it. Okay, so we don't really answer and resolve that
issue whether you could whether you could actually plant the stuff on
שביעית itself. Obviously the משנה mishna suggests not because the משנה mishna
talks about the wild growth. All right, now we continue. כיצד הוא
עושה? Keitzad hu oseh? Now כיצד הוא עושה Keitzad hu oseh is
going back on the משנה mishna, where it says you're paying the
people that are watching the grain. Now the question is the following.
You have the sanctified money. So Charlie here's been watching the grain
and cutting it in שמיטה and I'm going to give it to
him and I'm going to pay him. Oh you've been watching for
ten days, here's ten שקל shekel or whatever I pay him per
day. Where did the קדושה kedusha of that money go? Right? Normally
you use that money to buy an object, to buy the animal,
to buy the grain, then the קדושה kedusha transfers from the money
to the object and you have this holy animal, this קדוש kadosh
thing and now it's a קרבן. korban. Or you have the sanctified
grain. But if I'm paying for labor, where is the קדושה kedusha
of the money transferring? So what would you do? Right?
Why isn't it a type of מעילה? me'ilah?
Well that's it's another way of asking the question. Okay, yeah.
Isn't isn't the money for the upkeep of the temple coming from
consecrated money?
Well which is a similar question. So let's take a look. Okay.
So it is a general question that can be asked about where
do you how do you pay people for their labor with sanctified
funds? Okay. Now again we'll see later about what about what funds
are used for what, but this we specifically said is the שקל,
shekel, תרומת הלשכה, Trumat Halishkah, which actually has the the money is
itself sanctified. So let's take a look. So כיצד הוא עושה, keitzad
hu oseh, what would you do? נוטל מעות מן השולחני. Noteil ma'ot
min hashulchani. You let a שולחני, shulchani, normally that's a money changer
but presumably what they would also do is you know they'd lend
money so they have a lot of available funds. So you go
to your friend the banker and the banker gives pays Charlie his
hundred
dollars, okay? ונותן לקוצרים v'noten lakotzrim and you give it to those
that are going to harvest the grain
ולשומרים v'lishomrim and you pay them, and the bank pays you with
unsanctified fund.
עד שלא יקרב העומר, ad she-lo yikarev ha-Omer, and you pay them
with this thing even before it's time for bringing the עומר. ומביא
מעות מתרומת הלשכה, u-mevi ma'ot mi-trumat halishka, now we bring the hundred
dollars from the תרומת הלשכה, trumas ha-lishka ומחללן עליו. u-mechallelan alav. Now
Charlie goes ahead and he gives me the grain that he harvested.
So I say oh, so I'm going to give you a hundred
שקל shekel or I should not give you, I'm holding onto the
hundred שקל. shekel. You've already been paid for all your work from
the bank, okay? So I have hold onto the hundred שקל, shekel,
you so have the grain and what I'm going to say is
I take the sanctity of the grain and I transfer of the
hundred שקל shekel and I transfer it to the grain. So Charlie
doesn't get any of that hundred שקל. shekel. That stays in the
בית המקדש's Beit Hamikdash. you know ownership. What do we do with
it now? Now we have an unsanctified hundred שקל, shekel, you know
what we have to do with it? Have to repay the bank.
Pay the bank. Exactly. So the bank pays Charlie for his labor,
Charlie then freely gives us the עומר, the wheat that he harvested.
He's already been fully paid by the bank. We transfer the קדושה
kedusha to an object, to the grain, and then we use the
hundred dollars to pay back the bank. Okay, that's the way we
do it. So then the גמרא Gemara's has a simple question, the
גמרא Gemara says,
ותבוא כן, v'tavo ken, is it good right to do that? Meaning
meaning it doesn't stop the issue, but the question is that's it's
not worth a hundred dollars. Meaning Charlie had to be paid a
hundred dollars because he had to watch it for all that time.
But the actual grain itself was not worth a hundred שקל. shekel.
How am I supposed to transfer a hundred שקל shekel onto that
grain? So רבי יצחק בשם רבי בא, Rabbi Yitzchak be-shem Rabbi Ba,
כל מה שיתן הן הן דמיו משער ראשונה. Kol mah she-yiten hein
hein damav misha'ar rishona. Yeah, whatever, whatever you're going to pay for
it, retroactively we'll say that that is its value. It's a little
bit of a trick, but basically yes, you have a hundred שקל,
shekel, so you and you need to transfer the קדושה, kedusha, that
retroactively is the value of the grain.
He still basically pay $20 a pound for שווארמה shawarma because because
of the labor that goes into it.
So it's more valuable.
Yeah, although but here remember if it was a private if if
even during the שמיטה, one of the reasons he has to be
paid is he's watching the grain on an ongoing basis, you know,
which is disproportionate to the normal amount of labor even during the
שמיטה, because I can just go out to the field, grab some
free grain and whatever. So it is a little disproportionate. But you're
right, very often if there's a labor cost, that labor cost becomes
the cost of the commodity, and if it's a higher cost at
certain times. Okay, it could be that the גמרא's Gemara question was
otherwise. Was... let's read the next case. So the גמרא Gemara says
like
this: תני ותני ברייתא, Tani u-tana baraita, אף לפיתחי אבנים כן, af
l'pitchei avanim ken, you would do the same for the people that
would carve stones that you would use for the
בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash כיצד הוא עושה, Keitzad hu oseh, what would
you do? נוטל מעות משולחני ונותן לחוצבין ולסתתים, Notel ma'ot mi-shulchani ve-noten
le-chotzvin ve-lasatatin, you have the bank pay the carvers, the
hewers, ולסתתים, ve-lasatatin, and the carvers, עד שלא תינתן על גבי הדימוס
ad she-lo tinaten al gabei ha-dimos before you put it on top
of the... sort of you know, דימוס dimos is the like layer
of stones.
ומשניתנה על הדימוס, U-mi-she-nitanah al ha-dimos, once it's put on the layer
stones and the brick and the big stone is done, מביא מעות
מתרומת הלשכה ומחלל עליהן... עליה. mevi ma'ot mi-trumat ha-lishkah u-mechallel aleihen... aleha.
And you so then you take the money and you transfer the
קדושה kedusha to the stone, and then you take the money and
you repay the banker. So the גמרא Gemara says: ותבוא כן? Ve-tavo
ken? Is that really the right way? Is that really like appropriate?
Is that an equivalent amount? רבי יוסי בי רבי בון בשם שמואל:
Rabbi Yose be-reibi Bun be-shem Shmuel: כל מה שיתן הן הן דמיו
משער ראשונה. Kol mah she-yiten hein hein damav misha'ar rishona. Same point.
Now, here the question is like, you know, why isn't it the
right amount? If that's what it costs to make a carved stone,
then that's the cost of the stone. So some say well again,
maybe the workers, you know, maybe you know maybe they had an
accident and the first few stones didn't come out okay and this
stone did come out okay and you actually had stipulated with them
that you're paying them for their ongoing labor, which means even incidental
costs and even costs you know when things got messed up and
they would normally would not factor into the cost of the object
have to be covered. So that's how the מפרשים mefarshim understand the
question. And the answer is yeah, okay, retroactively we'll say that is
that really is the cost of the object itself. Okay, and this
is how we do this twist.
This is such a beautiful... just might be a beautiful description of
the making of Herodian stones.
You know, yeah, yeah, yeah, the דימוס dimos and the carving and
the cutting, right. Yep. Okay, now let's take a look at the
next משנה, mishna turn the page. פרה ושעיר המשתלח. Parah ve-sa'ir ha-mishtale'ach.
Now more things that are bought with the שקל, shekel, which might
not be so obvious to be considered קרבן korban, ציבור. So let's
take a look. פרה, Parah, the פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah. Now that's
not exactly a קרבן. korban It's slaughtered outside the בית המקדש, Beit
Hamikdash but it's called a חטאת. And in many ways we treat
it like a קרבן. korban. The blood is sprinkled towards the בית
המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So that can be bought with these communal funds.
But again you don't just buy... it's not anything that's communal, only
קרבנות korbanot ציבור. So the question is what fits in that category
for being bought by the שקל. shekel. ושעיר המשתלח, Ve-sa'ir ha-mishtale'ach, the
שעיר sa'ir that is sent לעזאזל. la-Azazel.
Now
that's not a קרבן. korban, So why can that be bought? So
the answer is it can be bought because you don't know which
is going to be which. So you have to buy two. So
therefore, so you because you have to buy two and they start
by coming together, you can use the שקל shekel to buy both
of them. לשון של זהורית, Lashon shel zehorit, the the crimson strand,
which actually was... it is not the strand that you is going
to be for the... when you push the שעיר sa'ir over the
over the thing and the thing turns white, we'll talk about that
in a minute. This actually is what was thrown into the fire
of the פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah. The תורה Torah says you throw
that in and you throw in some hyssop and so this is
part of making the קרבן, korban so this is seen as the
קרבן korban itself. The same way in a guess that the נסכים
nesachim are seen as a קרבן korban. ציבור, this is part of
the way you bring the what the פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah. Now,
all of those באים מתרומת הלשכה ba'im mi-trumat ha-lishkah come from the
תרומה, Trumah the taking of the moneys from the לשכה of the
שקל. shekel. כבש פרה וכבש שעיר המשתלח. Keves parah ve-keves sa'ir ha-mishtale'ach.
Now they would make a ramp when they would take the פרה
אדומה Parah Adumah out to where they would take it, they would
make this like double bridge almost, a bridge a ramp on top
of a ramp to protect it from טומאה. tum'ah. Also, what the
משנה Mishnah teaches in יומא Yoma is that they would have a
special getaway ramp for the שעיר המשתלח sa'ir ha-mishtale'ach and the guy
runs from it so that just people would like attack the goat
and say like and attack the person running and they pull hair
from it: get out of here, you know, take get rid of
our sins. So they needed a safe exit ramp. So that is
what they have for the שעיר המשתלח. Se'ir Hamishtaleach.
It is some kind of ש, shin, כבש? kevesh?
A כבש kevesh for a ramp. Yeah you're right, כבש keves is
a sheep. כבש, kevesh, right, I'm sorry, כבש kevesh for a ramp.
Thank you. כבש פרה, Kevash para, וכבש שעיר המשתלח, vekevesh se'ir hamishtaleach,
ולשון שבין קרניו uleshon shebein karnav and now we got to talk
about the string between the horns of the שעיר, se'ir, ואמת
המים וחומת העיר ומגדלותיה veamat hamayim vechomat ha'ir umigdaloteiha and now this
is
obvious, the sort of a channel of water maybe particularly the channel
that went through the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash that they would use
or but even not בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. related, the walls of
ירושלים Yerushalayim and its towers, וכל צרכי העיר, vechol tzorchei ha'ir, anything
needed for ירושלים, Yerushalayim, באין משיירי הלשכה. ba'in misheyarei halishkah. Now that
is not a קרבן. korban So obviously we start with the things
that's closest to a
קרבן, korban. like the string between the horns and the ramps, but
the point is these are things that are used for קרבנות, korbanot,
but they are not a קרבן korban and therefore if it does
not come from the from the תרומת הלשכה, trumas ha-lishka. it comes
from the שיירי הלשכה. Sheyarei Halishkah. You will remember that the משנה
said yesterday or the גמרא gemara. said that when you take the
תרומה truma from the money, from the שקל, shekel, what's left over
becomes desanctified, right, except according to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. So if
it became desanctified through the תרומת הלשכה, Trumat HaLishka now it can
be used for even non-קרבנות korbanot. and even non-קדושה kedusha purposes. It
can be used to strengthen the walls of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, so you
use it for these municipal and these communal needs which were even
non-sanctified, that's what you do with the שיירי הלשכה. Sheyarei Halishkah. אבא
שאול אומר, Abba Shaul omer, כבש פרה כהנים גדולים עושים משל עצמן.
kevesh para konim gedolim osim mishel atzman. Actually for the פרה אדומה,
para adumah, there that was the private donations from the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol and they did not need to use communal funds at
all. מותר שיירי לשכה מה היו עושים בהן? Motar sheyarei lishkah mah
hayu osim bahen? Now what do you do with what's left over
from what's left over? Right, you did the תרומה truma? and then
you had all this funds left over here and that was desanctified
and you used it to strengthen the city. Now comes the end
of the year and you even have leftover from that, you didn't
even use up all the funds. What are you going to do
with this money? We should only have such problems. So what would
you do with it? מה היו עושים בהן? Mah hayu osim bahen?
לוקחים בהן יינות שמנים וסלתות והשכר להקדש. Lokchim bahen yeinot shemanim vesoltot
vehaschar lehekdesh. You would buy wine and oil and flour and you
would sell it to the people coming to the בית המקדש. beis
hamikdash You'd set up a little shop and we would pocket the
difference. Now of course it doesn't tell you what you would do
with the profit. Still the question is what are you going to
do with all of that money? But anyway that's what you would
say. בית המקדש beis hamikdash would use the money to they'd invest
their funds if you have anything left over essentially invest it. Okay
do a side business here with selling wine and oil. דברי רבי
ישמעאל. Divrei Rabbi Yishmael. That's what רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says. רבי
עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer,
השכר להקדש, haschar lehekdesh, that's
the הקדש hekdesh gets the profit. So you go into business and
then we'll just use it to make a profit.
Who's that? The כהנים? Kohanim?
No, it's the leftover funds. Who's selling it? I don't know, we
hire people to sell it. I don't know who's selling it. We
have leftover money. What do you do with your money? Let's get
our money to work for us, let's invest it. No, it's שיירי
הלשכה, Sheyarei Halishkah, the שיירי הלשכה Sheyarei Halishkah was desanctified because you
took the תרומה. truma Let's again you took the תרומה truma from
all the שקל, shekel, that תרומה truma, was used for קרבנות korbanot
ציבור, we've just listed things that are considered קרבנות korbanot, ציבור, it
has to be a קרבן korban, proper. Everything left in that room
is שיירי הלשכה, Sheyarei Halishkah, that's the שיריים, that is used for
desanct that it became desanctified, you can even build the walls of
ירושלים Yerushalayim with it. Come the end of the year and there's
even leftover funds there, so then the חכמים say, then רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael says invest it. Okay makes do a little business.
So they might have subcontractors guys that they were doing work with
and this is here take this and invest it.
Yeah I mean or the גזבר, Gizbar, somebody is in charge of
the funds and he goes ahead and he starts uses the money
for doing this side business. Okay now רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says
let's take a look
what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says. By the way, the קרבן עדה
Korban Edah says it's not even necessarily leftover at the end of
the year. It might just be that we have no pressing need
for these funds, right? We've there's no
nothing הלואי halevai we should live in a time that there's nothing
that needs to be done in terms of the walls of the
city in terms of all that stuff is perfect and we still
have leftover money. What do we do with it?
Ultimately because the גזבר Gizbar whoever's in charge of that so ultimately
the profits from those investments are going into
the בית המקדש's Beit HaMikdash, account.
In other words, it's the person who we want to entrust someone
with a portfolio to make more money. Exactly.
Look someone has to make a decision when it says you use
it for
the wall the city and the towers. Somebody has to make a
decision what needs fixing, who to hire, we're going to submit bids
I mean there's a whole thing there's a lot of money involved.
Right. So whoever's in charge the גזבר Gizbar and then there's money
left over so the point is here you know invest it. For
a rainy day. So that's the position of רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael.
So the person who invested is the גזבר Gizbar כהן?
Kohen? Presumably, yes.
So the administrator of the מקדש Mikdash. was a כהן? Kohen? Right.
Exactly, yes.
Okay. Now, so that's what רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says. רבי עקיבא
אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says, אין משתכרין בשל
הקדש. ein mistakrin beshel hectesh. You don't use הקדש hectesh money to
do a business. It's not appropriate for a הקדש. hectesh. So I
mean, it reminds us sort of about, you know, the Jesus upturning
the money changers in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
You know, you don't go ahead and say, oh, okay, so now
we're also going to do a little bit of a side business.
It undermines the, you know, the sanctity of it and also look,
there is so much money going through the בית המקדש's Beit HaMikdash
hands with all this שקל Shekel and, you know, hiring people to
do all this type of stuff. You don't want it to look
like their focus is on making a profit. So you do not
want הקדש hectesh to be in business for itself.
That's what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says. אין משתכרין בשל הקדש ein
mistakrin beshel hectesh אף לא משל עניים. af lo mishel aniyim. And
similarly, and this is maybe less obvious, if you collected funds for
the עניים aniyim and you distributed funds and you have leftover, do
you what do you do with it? Do you just put it
in your mattress? Do you put it in the money market? Do
you invest it in the stock market? And he says you even
for the עניים aniyim you're not supposed to go ahead and, you
know, try to make a business out of it. Now, is it
that it's not appropriate? It looks again like maybe you're lining your
pockets. I mean, again, if you're in charge of the communal, you
know, charities, I mean we know all these stories about, about right,
about presidents of major charities that line their pockets. So you know,
it could be that that's the concern. It could also be that,
you know, the stock market can also go down. It doesn't always
it doesn't always go up. So maybe the point is you don't
fool around with that money and put it at risk. But it
could also be to be similar to I think the point of
the מקדש. You don't want anybody to be sort of the והייתם
נקיים veheyitem nekiyim idea from the other day. Okay, so let's keep
on going. Now, מותר התרומה מה
היו עושים בה? mosar hatruma ma hayu osim ba? Now,
let's say you actually had the תרומה itself, not the what was
left behind. And the end of the year came and you didn't
use up all the money in the baskets. You so what do
you do with that leftover money? And that is sanctified. The שירי
לשכה shirei lishka became de-sanctified. What do you do with the leftover
תרומה? מה היו עושים בה? ma hayu osim ba?
ריקועי זהב ציפוי לבית קדשי הקדשים. rikuei zahav tzipui leveit kodesh hakodashim.
You would use it for gold plating on the walls of the
קדשי הקדשים. Kodesh HaKodashim. So why of all things I don't know
that you would do that. I mean, why is that comparable to
קרבנות korbanot, ציבור? Hard for me to understand and why of all
things that's where it would go. רבי ישמעאל אומר, Rabbi Yishmael omer,
מותר הפירות קיץ המזבח. mosar haperos kayitz hamizbe'ach. What's leftover from the
פירות? peros? Who's talking about פירות? peros? So we'll see what the
גמרא gemara discusses what that means. That would go for the קיץ
המזבח kayitz hamizbe'ach for the like dessert of the מזבח. mizbe'ach, That
the קיץ המזבח kayitz hamizbe'ach is this what I mentioned before that
when nothing is happening on the מזבח, mizbe'ach you use some communal
funds for bringing עולות olos so it looks like the מזבח mizbe'ach
is busy so it does not look, you know, so it does
not look disrespectful. So he says that's what you would do. You
understand it at least. You're using the שקל Shekel for some type
of, you know, קרבן. korban At least it makes sense. It's not
an obligatory קרבן korban but at least it's some type of a
קרבן. korban מותר תרומה תרומה mosar truma truma I'm sorry, I'm sorry,
no, I misstated it because actually it says the מותר פירות mosar
peros went to קיץ המזבח. kayitz hamizbe'ach. We don't even know what
מותר פירות mosar peros means. We'll see that. מותר פירות mosar peros
went to קיץ המזבח. kayitz hamizbe'ach. מותר תרומה לכלי שרת. mosar truma
liklei shares. What you do with the leftover funds for the תרומה
is you use it to buy the various vessels of the בית
המקדש. Beit HaMikdash, Again, what the why that's appropriate for the שקל
Shekel of all things is not clear to me. רבי עקיבא אומר,
Rabbi Akiva omer, מותר תרומה לקיץ המזבח. mosar truma lekayitz hamizbe'ach. Yeah,
I was jumping ahead. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says, no, the leftover
funds you use for the for the קיץ המזבח kayitz hamizbe'ach for
these עולות olos when the מזבח mizbe'ach is not busy. That you
can understand, right? Because that is at least buying a קרבן korban
with it and that's what the תרומה was basically for.
לכלי שרת, liklei shares, why do you think that's inappropriate?
No, not inappropriate, not like it's wrong, but just of all things
why would if you have to decide what is the leftover שקל
Shekel going to go to, why would you choose, oh, gold plating
the קדשי הקדשים, Kodesh HaKodashim, כלי שרת? klei shares? Presumably, you'd want
it to be something that's more about a קרבן, korban which is
what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says. You would want it to be
more in line with why it was originally purchased, I would think,
why it was originally collected, which is what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
says. מותר נסכים לכלי שרת. mosar nesachim liklei shares. However, if you
have leftover funds that were used on for the for the wine
and the flour, that would go for the כלי שרת klei shares
because רבי חנניה
סגן הכהנים אומר, Rabbi Chananya Segan HaKohanim omer, and רבי חנניה Rabbi
Chananya the assistant כהן Kohen says, so he probably would know, מותר
נסכים קיץ המזבח. mosar nesachim kayitz hamizbe'ach. No, the leftover נסכים nesachim,
would go to the קיץ המזבח kayitz hamizbe'ach because here there's a
similarity. What do you do with the נסכים, nesachim the wine and
the flour? You burn it fully, you put it on the מזבח
mizbe'ach and it gets completely, you know, used. So the קיץ המזבח...
kayitz hamizbe'ach... מזבח is an עולה, so that would be a similar
use. So leftover funds for the נסכים nesachim would go to the
קיץ המזבח. keitz hamizbe'ach. מותרי התרומה לכלי שרת mosre hatruma likli sharet
and leftover תרומה, that would go for a כלי שרת kli sharet
וזה וזה לא היו מודים בפירות ve-ze ve-ze lo hayu modim be-peirot
and they would not agree with פירות. peirot. We don't even know
what פירות peirot is. I'm not going to discuss it now. We'll
get to it tomorrow. So you have a lot of possibilities of
what it can be used for but you don't have any clear
reasons and you know presumably you want it to be something that
somehow is analogous or in line with what its original function was.
Not exactly clear what these different opinions are. I also want to
say by the way that מותרי נסכים mosre nesachim is not clear
to me whether that means the נסכים nesachim that you bought, the
communal נסכים nesachim. that you bought with the שקל shekel and in
a way then why isn't it just
מותרי תרומה mosrei truma because you have all this money, one of
the things you buy with it is the נסכים. nesachim What does
that mean you bought too much wine and then you sold it
back? I mean I'm not exactly getting how the money is labeled
נסכים nesachim money. It might be talking about private. It might mean
that I set aside funds
for נסכים nesachim, for my קרבן korban, and I had leftover and
then I go to you the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. and I
say I had a hundred dollars or twenty dollars leftover from the
money I set aside for my נסכים, what should I do with
it? And they'll say don't worry just give it to me. So
anyway
but they put that in the מותרי נסכים mosre nesachim fund. So
I think מותרי נסכים mosre nesachim makes more sense if it's private
money, but you know then it would be somewhat different than some
of these other these other cases. Let's take a look at the
גמרא. כבש פרה, kevish para, רבי שמואל בר נחמן בשם רבי יונתן,
Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachman beshem Rabbi Yonasan, ג' לשונות הן, gimel leshonos
hen, there are three strings. של שעיר בסלע, shel sa'ir ba-sela, the
one of the goat that the שעיר המשתלח sa'ir hamishtale'ach that you
would leave by the rock, right, they would put it by the
rock to see if it changed colors. של- sorry, that is what's-
but that's not what סלע sela means here. They would- they would
put it by the rock but סלע sela. here means it's the
weight of a
סלע. sela, של מצורע בשקל shel metzora be-shekel or cost a סלע,
sela. the one of a מצורע metzora which they would use also
in the you know in the burning and in the ritual of
the מצורע, metzora, that would be a שקל shekel which is half
a סלע. sela. So that would be half as much string, cost
half as much or weigh half as much. Some say we're talking
here about weights. של פרה shel para and of the פרה אדומה
para aduma בשתי סלעים bishtei sela'im is two סלעים. sela'im. Okay, so
it would be twice as much as everything. So why is that?
So well let's first read one other opinion. רבי חונא דברת חברין,
Rabbi Chuna d'bras chavrin, we had that once before ברת חברין, bras
chavrin, so the same person. רבי חוניא ברת חברין, Rabbi Chunya bras
chavrin, רבי בא בר זבדא בשם רבי שמעון בן חלפתא, Rabbi Ba
bar Zavda beshem Rabbi Shimon ben Chalafsa, של פרה בשתי סלעים ומחצה.
shel para bishtei sela'im va-mechetza. Actually the one they would use for
the פרה אדומה para aduma wouldn't just be two, it would be
two and a half סלע. sela ואית דמפקין לישנא בעשרה זוז, ve-is
de-mafkin lishna be-asara zuz, some say that some have- say the way
he said it was not two and a half שקל shekel but
ten זוז. zuz. There's four זוז zuz to a סלע sela so
two and a half סלע sela is ten זוז. zuz. So like
it's איכא דאמרי ika de'amri but it's a very trivial איכא דאמרי.
ika de'amri. Rather than saying two and a half סלע he said
ten זוז. zuz. Now what's the reason for these different ones? Well
the reason the פרה אדומה para aduma one is so much is
basically because it has to be heavy because you're supposed to throw
it into the burning fire and therefore it's supposed to be heavy.
The reason the one of the שעיר המשתלח sa'ir hamishtale'ach was twice
as much as the מצורע metzora was because you would cut it
in half, right. If you remembered you would divide it and you'd
put half of it on a rock and half of it you
know would sort of you know would the- would be on the-
on the horns of the goat. So therefore it needed to be
twice as big as the one you would use for the מצורע.
metzora. So that's anyway just these different types of- of strings and
their different costs or their different weight. רבי יהודה בשם רבי שמואל
Rabbi Yehuda beshem Rabbi Shmuel says the following: תלמידי חכמים המלמדין, talmidei
chachamim ha-melamdin, now we're going to get interesting possible uses for the
funds and I have to tell you this is all going to
be the funds of the תרומת הלשכה Trumat HaLishka. which is supposed
to be for קרבנות korbanot and the whole point we've been making
is only for קרבן korban. and not for צורכי קרבן, korban, not
for attendant things that isn't the קרבן korban? itself. So you'll help
me figure out why some of this makes sense. רבי יהודה בשם
רבי שמואל, Rabbi Yehuda beshem Rabbi Shmuel, תלמידי חכמים המלמדין את הכהנים
הלכות שחיטה הלכות קבלה הלכות זריקה. talmidei chachamim ha-melamdin es ha-kohanim hilchos
shechita hilchos kabala hilchos zerika. How about the sages that would teach
the חכמים, right, it's very interesting again this assumption that the rabbis
ultimately control the בית המקדש tends to be an assumption that the-
that the גמרא has. So here not controlling it but they have
all the knowledge. So the sages that are teaching or the rabbinical
students that are teaching the כהנים kohanim all the laws, where do
they get paid from? נוטלין שכרן מתרומת הלשכה. notlin secharan mi-trumas ha-lishka.
They get it from the שקל. shekel. Now I gotta tell you
what sense does that make? Right? First of all you have to
figure out how do they get paid, the whole problem about the
banker and transferring but what object is the קדושה kedusha going to
be transferred to here? There's comp- there's no object at all number
one. But number two is it's only supposed to go for קרבנות,
it's not supposed to go for anything that's not a קרבן korban?
even things that are associated with קרבנות. Okay let's keep on reading.
רבי יפתא בר רדיפה בשם רבי אמי, Rabbi Yifta bar Redifa beshem
Rabbi Ami, מבקרי מומי קדשים mevakrei mumei kodshim נוטלין שכר מתרומת הלשכה.
notlin sechar mi-trumas ha-lishka. The people that would be check the animals
for the קרבנות to make sure there are no blemishes, they'd also
get paid from the תרומת הלשכה. Trumat HaLishka! Again, that's not the
קרבן korban itself. רבי אחא רבי תנחום בר חייא בשם רבי סימלאי
מגיהי ספר העזרה נוטלין שכרם מתרומת הלשכה. Rebbi Acha Rebbi Tanchum bar
Chiya beshem Reb Simlai magihey Sefer HaAzara notlin secharam mitrumat halishka. The
people that would correct the ספר sefer of the עזרה Azara would
also get paid. Now that's a fascinating
question, what is the ספר sefer of the עזרה? Azara? So some
of the מפרשים mefarshim turn to a rabbinic source that says that
what they did is they actually created a hybrid ספר תורה. Sefer
Torah. They had three versions of the תורה Torah with slightly different
texts and they took the one that was sort of the, they
did a democratic approach, and when there was any difference in texts
they did the one that had two of them outweighing the third,
and that was the ספר תורה Sefer Torah that they kept stored
in the בית המקדש, and that would be the source, the ספר
תורה Sefer Torah they would use to, on the basis of that,
make sure that all the other ספרי תורה Sifrei Torah were done
correctly. So some say that's what it refers to, that they're actually
going ahead and checking all the ספרי תורה Sifrei Torah against this
ספר sefer in the בית המקדש. Some say it means עזרה Azara
here, or some have the גרסא girsa interestingly, not ספר העזרה Sefer
HaAzara but ספר עזרא. Sefer Ezra. So that, you know, that עזרא
Ezra brought back, עזרא הסופר, Ezra HaSofer, and that he had the
most accurate ספר. sefer. Others say ספר עזרה Sefer Azara is the
ספר תורה Sefer Torah that the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol would read
from on יום כיפור Yom Kippur in the עזרה. Azara. So it
does not mean that it was the, and they would correct it
in case they'd have to proofread it and they would correct it.
But again, why are you using תרומת הלשכה Trumat HaLishka for these
funds? Let's read a little bit more. גידול בר בנימין בשם רב
אסי שני דייני גזילות, Gidul bar Binyamin beshem Rav Assi shenei dayanei
gezelot, some have גזירות, gezerot, נוטלין שכרם מתרומת הלשכה. notlin secharam mitrumat
halishka. There would be two people in the בית המקדש that would
constantly be dealing with sort of like, you know, בית דין Beit
Din types of matters, and they also would get paid. They had
the, they couldn't do any other job, they spent their whole days
in the בית המקדש, they'd be the in-house דיינים, dayanim, and they
would get paid from תרומת הלשכה. Trumat HaLishka But it's תרומת הלשכה!
You know, again, it's supposed to be only קרבן, and where is
the קדושה kedusha transferring to? So שמואל אמר נשים האורגות בפרוכת, Shmuel
amar nashim haorgot baparochet, women who, whenever we talk about weaving or
sewing it mentions women, the women who would weave the פרוכת, parochet,
נוטלין שכרם מתרומת הלשכה. notlin secharam mitrumat halishka. They'd also get paid
from that fund. רבי חונא אומר לא מתרומת בדק הבית. Rebbi Chuna
omer no mitrumat Bedek HaBayit. No, they'd get paid for the funds
that were stored up to fix actually, you know, the actual structure
of the בית המקדש. So מה פליג? ma palig? So what's the
debate about about where you would pay the פרוכת parochet funds for?
שמואל עביד ליה כקרבן, Shmuel avid lei kikorban, רב הונא עביד ליה
כבניין. Rav Huna avid lei kibinyan. So רב הונא Rav Huna or
רב חונא Rav Chuna says that it's like the structure. Yes, it's
a curtain, but is a curtain part of the structure or is
it a hanging on the structure? So he said a curtain is
like the structure, you'd use the funds of בדק הבית. Bedek HaBayit.
שמואל Shmuel makes it like a קרבן. Now makes it like a
קרבן, again you sort might need it in order to bring the
קרבנות, we're going to discuss tomorrow whether you need certain things in
order to allow you to bring קרבנות, maybe you needed it, but
what does this mean again makes it like a קרבן? And the
real question here, some try to switch the גרסא girsa up, but
the real question and with this I'll end is, how are you
using תרומת הלשכה funds for something that is not a קרבן? And
what the מפרשים mefarshim all say is, this is going to be
a little disappointing, is that yeah basically בית דין stipulate that if
we have to, you know, that if we need to use the
תרומת הלשכה funds for all the following things that then retroactively it'll
never have been sanctified for that purpose, it'll be חולין chulin and
we can use it for that. So we move from having the
funds sanctified and a very narrow use of only קרבנות to saying
but when we want we can desanctify it and use it for
a lot of other things that are not קרבן-related. Okay, so we
will pick up with that tomorrow.